Chapter 94. A squeeze of the hand.
That whale of stubs, so dearly purchased, was duly brought to the
Peekquad's side, where all those cutting and hoisting operations previously
detailed were regularly gone through, even to the bailing of the H Highleberg
ton or case. While some were occupied with this latter duty, others were
employed in dragging away the larger tubs so soon as filled with the sperm,
and when the proper time arrived, this same sperm was carefully manipulated,
airgoing to the triworks, of which a naan, it had cooled and crystallized to
such a degree that when, with several others, I sat down before a large
Constantine's bath of it, I found it strangely concreted into lumps here and
there, rolling about, out in the liquid part. It was our business to squeeze
these lumps back into fluid. A sweet and anxious duty. No wonder that in old
times this sperm was such a favorite cosmetic, such a clearer, such a
sweetener, such a softener, such a delicious mllifier. After having my
hands in it for only a few minutes, my fingers felt like eels and began, as it
were, to serpentine and spiralize.
As I sat there at my ease, cross-legged on the deck, after the bitter exertion
at the windless, under a blue tranquil sky, the ship under indolent sail, and
gliding so serenely along, as I bathed my hands among those soft, gentle
globules of infiltrated tissues, woven almost within the hour, as they richly
broke to my fingers and discharged all their opulence like fully ripe grapes
their wine, as I snuffed up that uncontaminated aroma, literally and
truly like the smell of spring violets.
I declare to you that for the time I lived as in a musky meadow. I forgot all
about our horrible oath. In that inexpressable sperm, I washed my hands
and my heart of it. I almost began to credit the old paracelson superstition
that sperm is of rare virtue in allaying the heat of anger. While bathing in that
bath, I felt divinely free from all ill will or petulence or malice of any sort whatsoever.
Squeeze, squeeze, squeeze. All the morning long I squeezed that sperm till
I myself almost melted into it. I squeezed that sperm till a strange sort
of insanity came over me, and I found myself unwittingly squeezing my
co-laborer's hands in it, mistaking their hands for the gentle globules.
Such an abounding, affectionate, friendly, loving feeling did this
avocation beget, that at last I was continually squeezing their hands, and
looking up into their eyes sentimentally, as much as to say, "Oh,
my dear fellow beings, why should we longer cherish any social assurbies, or
know the slightest ill humor or envy?
Come, let us squeeze hands all round.
Nay, let us all squeeze ourselves into each other. Let us squeeze ourselves
universally into the very milk and sperm of kindness.
Would that I could keep squeezing that sperm forever. For now, since by many
prolonged repeated experiences, I have perceived that in all cases man must
eventually lower or at least shift his conceit of attainable felicity, not
placing it anywhere in the intellect or the fancy, but in the wife, the heart,
the bed, the table, the saddle, the fireside, the country. Now that I have
perceived all this, I am ready to squeeze case eternally. In thoughts of
the visions of the night, I saw long rows of angels in paradise, each with
his hands in a jar of spermaceti.
Now, while discoursing on sperm, it behooves to speak of other things akin
to it in the business of preparing the sperm whale for the tri works. First
comes white horse, so-called, which is obtained from the tapering part of the
fish, and also from the thicker portions of his flukes. It is tough with
congealed tendons, a wad of muscle, but still contains some oil. After being
severed from the whale, the white horse is first cut into portable oblongs,
airgoing to the mincer. They look much like blocks of birkshire marble.
Plum pudding is the term bestowed upon certain fragmentaryary parts of the
whale's flesh here and there adhering to the blanket of blubber and often
participating to a considerable degree in its anxiousness. It is a most
refreshing convivial beautiful object to behold. As its name imports, it is of an
exceedingly rich modeled tint with a brie snowy and golden ground dotted with
spots of the deepest crimson and purple.
It is plums of rubies in pictures of citroen. Spite of reason, it is hard to
keep yourself from eating it. I confess that once I stole behind the formass to
try it. It tasted something, as I should conceive, a royal cutlet from the thigh
of Louis might have tasted, supposing him to have been killed the first day
after the venison season, and that particular venison season, contemporary
with an unusually fine vintage of the vineyards of Champagne.
There is another substance, and a very singular one, which turns up in the
course of this business, but which I feel it to be very puzzling adequately
to describe. It is called slobgallion, an appellation original with the
whaleman, and even so is the nature of the substance. It is an ineffably oozy,
stringy affair, most frequently found in the tubs of sperm after a prolonged
squeezing and subsequent decanting. I hold it to be the wondrously thin
ruptured membranes of the case coalescing.
Glurry, so-called, is a term properly belonging to right whalemen, but
sometimes incidentally used by the sperm fishermen. It designates the dark,
glutenous substance which is scraped off the back of the Greenland or right
whale, and much of which covers the decks of those inferior souls who hunt
that ignoble leviathan.
Nippers. Strictly this word is not indigenous to the whale's vocabulary,
but as applied by whaleman, it becomes so. A whaleman's nipper is the short,
firm strip of tendonous stuff cut from the tapering part of the Leviathan's
tail. It averages an inch in thickness, and for the rest is about the size of
the iron part of a hoe. edgewise moved along the oily deck, it operates like a
leather squelg, and by nameless blandishments, as of magic, allures
along with it all impurities.
But to learn all about these recondite matters, your best way is at once to
descend into the blubber room, and have a long talk with its inmates. This place
has previously been mentioned as the receptacle for the blanket pieces when
stripped and hoisted from the whale.
When the proper time arrives for cutting up its contents, this apartment is a
scene of terror to all Tyros, especially by night. On one side, lit by a dull
lantern, a space has been left clear for the workmen. They generally go in pairs,
a pike and gaffman, and a spademan. The whailing pike is similar to a frigot's
boarding weapon of the same name. The gaff is something like a boat hook. With
his gaff, the gaffman hooks on to a sheet of blubber and strives to hold it
from slipping as the ship pitches and lurches about. Meanwhile, the spade man
stands on the sheet itself, perpendicularly chopping it into the
portable horse pieces. This spade is sharp as hone can make it. The
spademan's feet are sholess. The thing he stands on will sometimes irresistibly
slide away from him like a sledge. If he
cuts off one of his own toes or one of his assistants, would you be very much
astonished? Toes are scarce among veteran blubber room men.